Hello everyone, and welcome. I’m Dr. Michael
Greger, coming to you from my treadmill to do
a webinar on thyroid issues, because it is one of
the most common questions I’m asked in my monthly
Q&As. First, though, just to allow slackers some
time to join and to reward those who are on time,
let’s do a quick little fun giveaway. I’m
going to show you a strange fruit or vegetable,
and the first person to correctly
identify said fruit or vegetable
will get a signed, personalized copy
of my latest book, How Not to Diet.
So we’re going to do it in the chat. What
you’ve got to do is go to the bottom of
the little Zoom screen, click the chat button,
and open a little sidebar. Then, at the bottom,
make sure you are chatting to both panelists
and attendees. Send chat to panelists and
attendees so everyone can see your chats,
so we can see who gets the right answer.
All right. So make sure the chat sidebar is open.
Are you ready? Get ready to type your guess.
The first person to get it right
wins the book. Are you ready?
Now, I was actually going to go grab one from the
local Asian market so I could hold it up, but I
didn’t have time. So I’m just going to show you a
picture. Who can tell me what this crazy thing is?
All right, first person. Let’s
see it. Let’s see the chat.
Oh my god, there’s like a million. Hopefully,
we’re going to be able to find this. Okay,
let’s see who got it. Okay, I’m scrolling
through the chat. It is not French fries.
It’s not ugli fruit. Okay. Oh my god,
we got a couple. It’s not ginger. Oh,
we got lots of right answers, but let’s see
who was the first one to get the right answer.
Boy, that’s the problem when you have
thousands of people on a call. This is great.
Okay, I think I got to the beginning.
And the first person to get it right...
It’s not a jackfruit. Not a durian. Not a
dragon fruit. Lots of jack— not a lychee,
not a lemon, not a durian. Ah, Sarah
Sierra, you did it. She was just
a panelist. She didn’t switch
over to panelists and attendees,
so I don’t think anyone can actually see her
text, but Sarah Sierra said Buddha’s hand.
I also would have accepted fingered citron,
or the Latin name Citrus medica sarcodactylis,
but the common terminology is Buddha’s hand. So
Sarah, NutritionFacts staff will reach out to you
and get your mailing address, and
we will get a book right out to you.
All right, let me see—should we
try one more? Raise your hand if
you want to do one more quick giveaway. Otherwise,
we’ll go straight to the webinar. What do
you think? Raise your hand. Let me know.
Okay. So if we get a thousand
hands raised, we’ll do it again,
because that’s about half the attendees.
We have about 2,300 people on the call.
We have about 700 hands raised. We have
about 800 hands raised. 900 hands raised.
Looks like we are going to go—we have a
thousand. All right. So we’ll do one more.
This one I actually had in my fridge because
they’ve become one of my favorite snacks.
So are you ready? Okay. Let me get this out
of the way. All right. Are you ready? Ready
to type? Ready to chat? Here we go. What are
these? And these are not grapefruits. In fact,
a grapefruit is a cross between this and
an orange that produces a grapefruit.
But what is this? Let’s see who won this
round, and then we’ll get to the webinar.
Okay. Now I’ve got to find out where this
started. Oh, I should have checked a clock,
because there are hundreds per
minute. Okay, here we go. Oh,
I see lots of right answers here. Let’s see where
the first one was. It is not a lychee. That would
be a big lychee. It’s not a pawpaw. It’s not
a barberry or a kumquat or a mango. Oh my god,
these are probably people who wrote their answer
before I showed it. That’s smart. That’s totally
smart. Oh my god, if I had a pawpaw, I would
totally be showing you a pawpaw right now.
And Amanda gets it. Amanda Beer gets pomelo at
12:04, beating out Carrie Nichols by mere seconds,
I’m sure. But we will reach out to you,
Amanda, and I will get you that cookbook.
All right. Okay, that was fun. But let us get
this webinar started. Just a few housekeeping
logistics. If you can’t hear me right now, there
are instructions in the email that was sent out
last week to tweak your audio settings. If at
any time you run into technical difficulties,
we have live Zoom staff standing by. In
fact, I will paste that link into the chat.
Although I don’t know—I just pasted that
to everybody in the chat if you want to get
that URL if they’re unable to help. We also
have NutritionFacts.org staff standing by,
though presumably if Zoom can’t help, I don't know
what we'll be able to do. Let me post that into
the chat box as well, that email address, just so
you have it handy if you ever run into problems.
Next up, please reserve the Q&A button that you
see in the Zoom window to ask content questions.
The webinar will go for an hour—super quick. This
is going to just speed by. I’ve reserved some time
for Q&A at the end, but please feel free to add
your questions throughout the webinar. In fact,
people were already typing in questions before
the webinar even started, so the NutritionFacts
team right now will compile them, and we’ll
get as many as possible answered at the end.
You may want to wait to see if I
cover it later on in the webinar,
but feel free to ask anytime. All right. You
do not have to worry about taking notes or
anything. Why? Because after the webinar is over,
not only will we send you a full recording of it,
but also a free link to download all the videos
in high definition so you can see the videos in
their full resolution glory, and you can stop
them, pause them, anything you want to do.
All right, let me start with a video
entitled, ‘Are vegans at risk for iodine
deficiency?’ Okay, let’s find my video. Okay.
Adequate dietary iodine is required
for normal thyroid function.
In fact, the two thyroid hormones
are named after how many
iodine atoms they
contain: T3 and T4.
Now, given that iodine is extensively
stored in the thyroid gland itself,
it's not something you
have to get every day,
but your overall diet needs
to have some good source.
Unfortunately, the common sources
aren't particularly health-promoting:
iodized salt, [and] dairy foods
because iodine-based cleansers
like betadine are used to sanitize
the udders, which results in some
iodine leaching into the milk.
They also add iodine to cattle feed,
and some commercial breads have
iodine-containing food additives.
So if you put people on a paleo-type
diet and cut out dairy and table salt,
they can develop an iodine deficiency,
even though they double
their seafood intake, which
can also be a source.
What about those switching to diets
centered around whole plant foods?
They're also cutting down
on ice cream and Wonder Bread,
and if they're not eating anything from
the sea—seaweed, sea vegetables—
they can run into the same problem.
Her parents reported striving to
feed her only the healthiest foods.
The 3-year-old only got plant-based,
unsalted, unprocessed foods
with no vitamin supplementation.
Now that could have been deadly.
With no vitamin B12, those on strictly
plant-based diets can develop
irreversible nerve damage, but
in this case, a goiter arose first
due to inadequate iodine intake.
Here's another case of veganism
as a cause of iodine deficient
hypothyroidism in a toddler after
weaning. Now before weaning,
he was fine because his mother
kept taking her prenatal vitamins,
which luckily contained iodine.
Most vegetarians and vegans are
apparently unaware of the importance
of iodine in pregnancy, just as clueless
as their omnivorous counterparts.
The American Thyroid Association and
the American Academy of Pediatrics
have recommended that women even
just planning on getting pregnant
should ingest a daily supplement that
contains 150 micrograms of iodine, yet
only 60% of prenatal vitamins marketed
in the US contain this essential mineral.
So, in spite of the recommendations,
about 40% lack it. Therefore, it's
extremely important that pregnant and
breastfeeding women read the labels
to ensure they're receiving
an adequate amount.
Women of reproductive age have
an average iodine level of 110,
which is fine for nonpregnant
individuals, but we'd really
like to see at least
150 in pregnancy.
It's basically a 24-hour urine test,
in which iodine sufficiency is defined
as 100 mcg/liter of pee in nonpregnant
adults, which your average vegan
fails to reach in the largest study
done to date, out of Boston.
The recommended average daily
intake is 150 mcg/day for most people,
which you can get in like a
cup and a half of cow's milk.
Sadly, plant-based milks are
typically not fortified with iodine,
averaging only about 3 mcg/cup.
In the largest systematic study to date,
although many plant-based milks are
fortified with calcium, they only found
just 3 of 47 fortified with iodine.
Those that were had as much as cow's
milk, but those that weren't fell short.
Plant-based milk companies brag about
enriching their milks with calcium,
and often vitamin B12, D, and vitamin A,
but only rarely are attempts made
to match the iodine content.
The only reason cow's milk has as
much as it does is that they enrich
the feed, or it comes
dripping off their udders.
So why don't plant-milk
companies add iodine, too?
I was told by a food scientist at
Silk that my carrageenan video
played a role in them
switching to another thickener.
Hopefully, they'll see this video
and consider adding iodine, too,
or some company will snatch at
the market advantage opportunity.
The researchers conclude that individuals
who consume plant-based milks
not fortified with iodine may be
at risk for iodine deficiency,
unless they consume alternative
dietary iodine sources,
the healthiest of which is sea
vegetables, which we'll cover next.
Okay. So to reiterate, one cause
of hypothyroidism—an underactive
thyroid gland—is inadequate iodine intake.
An underactive thyroid gland is especially
important for pregnant women and women even
considering pregnancy. That largest study of
vegan iodine status in Boston found most vegans
have insufficient intake. So what’s the best way
to get it? What’s the healthiest natural source
of iodine? That’s the name of the next video.
Dairy milk supplies between a quarter and
a half of the daily iodine requirement
in the United States, though milk
itself has little native iodine.
The milk iodine content is mainly
determined by factors like
the application of iodine-
containing teat disinfectants.
The iodine residues in milk
appear to originate
mainly from the contamination
of the teat surface.
The teats are sprayed or dipped with
like betadine-type disinfectants,
and the iodine just kind
of leaches into the milk.
Too bad most of the plant-
based milks on the market
aren't enriched
with iodine, too.
Fortified soy milk is probably
the healthiest of the plant milks,
but even if it was enriched with iodine,
what about the effects of soy
on thyroid function?
It's funny, when I searched the
medical literature on soy and thyroid,
this study popped up:
a cost-effective way to train
residents to do thyroid biopsies.
Just stick the ultrasound probe
right on top and go to town.
It turns out on ultrasound your
thyroid gland looks a lot like tofu.
Anyway, the idea that soy may
influence thyroid function
originated over eight decades ago when
marked thyroid enlargement was seen
in rats fed raw soybeans, though the
observation that people living in Asian
countries have consumed
soy foods for centuries
with no perceptible thyrotoxic effects
certainly suggests their safety.
The bottom line is there does
not seem to be a problem
with people who have
normal thyroid function.
However, soy foods may inhibit
the oral absorption of Synthroid,
thyroid hormone replacement
drugs, but so do all foods.
That's why we tell patients to take it
on an empty stomach. But you also
have to be getting enough iodine,
so it may be particularly important
for soy food consumers to make sure
their intake of iodine is adequate.
What's the best way to get iodine?
For those who use table salt,
make sure it's iodized.
Currently, only half of table
salt sold contains iodine,
and the salt used in processed
foods is typically not iodized.
Of course, ideally, we
shouldn't add salt at all.
Dietary salt is a public health hazard.
Think this title is a little over the top?
Dietary salt is the #1 dietary risk
factor for death on the planet Earth,
wiping out more than
three million people a year
twice as bad as not
eating your vegetables.
What's the best source of iodine, then?
Sea vegetables! You can get
a little iodine here and there
from a whole variety of foods,
but the most concentrated source
by far, with up to nearly 2,000%
of your daily allowance
in just a single gram—
which is like the weight
of a paperclip: seaweed.
Given that iodine is extensively stored
in the thyroid, it can be safely consumed
intermittently, meaning you
don't have to get it every day,
which makes seaweed use
in a range of foods attractive,
and occasional seaweed intake
enough to ensure iodine sufficiency.
However, some seaweed
should be used with caution
due to its overly high iodine
content, like kelp.
Too much iodine can
cause hyperthyroidism,
a hyperactive thyroid gland.
A woman presented
with a racing heartbeat, insomnia,
anxiety, and weight loss
thanks to taking just two
tablets a day containing kelp.
In my last video, I noted how the
average urinary iodine level of vegans
was less than the ideal levels, but
there was one kelp-eating vegan
with a urinary concentration over 9,000.
Adequate intake is when
you're peeing out 100 to 199.
Excessive iodine intake is when you
break 300; 9,437: way too much.
The recommended average daily intake
is 150 mcg/day for non-pregnant,
non-breastfeeding adults, and we may want
to stay below 600 on a day-to-day basis,
whereas a tablespoon of
kelp may contain 2,000.
I'd stay away from kelp
because it has too much,
and stay away from hijiki because
it contains too much arsenic.
Here's how much common seaweed
preparations should give you
an approximate daily allowance:
two nori sheets, you can literally
just nibble on them
as snacks like I do;
one teaspoon of dulse flakes, which
you can just sprinkle on anything;
one teaspoon of dried arame, which
is great for like adding to soups;
or one tablespoon of seaweed salad.
If iodine is concentrated in marine
foods, this raises the question
of how early hominins living in
continental areas could have met
their iodine requirements.
Well, here's what bonobos do,
perhaps our closest relatives.
During swamp visits, they
all forage aquatic herbs.
You can munch on aquatic plants yourself
by incorporating seaweed into your diet,
the healthiest natural source of iodine.
Okay, so we have covered iodine. Okay, hold on.
Okay, so we covered thyroid issues caused by
either too little or too much iodine intake,
but what about hypothyroidism or hyperthyroidism
caused by autoimmune diseases like Hashimoto’s
thyroiditis? That’s what we’ll turn
to next in my video, 'The Best Diet
for Hypothyroidism and Hyperthyroidism'.
And then I can finish eating my seaweed.
There are several autoimmune diseases
that affect the thyroid gland,
the most common being Graves' disease
and Hashimoto's thyroiditis.
Graves' disease results in hyperthyroidism,
an overactive thyroid gland.
Though slaughterhouses are
supposed to remove thyroid glands,
should some neck meat slip in,
you can suffer a similar syndrome
called hamburger thyrotoxicosis.
But that's not from your body making
too much thyroid hormone;
that's from your body eating
too much thyroid hormone.
Graves' disease is much more common,
and meat-free diets may be able to help
with both, as plant-based diets
may be associated
with a low prevalence
of autoimmune disease
in general, as observed, for example,
in rural sub-Saharan Africa.
Maybe it's because plants
are packed with antioxidants,
which are possible protective factors
against autoimmune diseases.
Maybe it's because plants are packed
with anti-inflammatory compounds.
After all, a whole food plant-based diet
is basically synonymous with
an anti-inflammatory diet. But you
don't know until you put it to the test.
It turns out the exclusion of all
animal foods was associated with
half the prevalence of hyperthyroidism
compared with omnivorous diets.
Lacto-ovo vegetarian and
fish-only diets were associated
with intermediate protection, but
a 52% lower odds of hyperthyroidism
among those eating strictly
plant-based diets.
This apparent protection may be due
to the exclusion of animal foods,
the benefits of plant foods, or both.
Animal foods, like meat, eggs,
and dairy products, may contain
high estrogen concentrations,
for example,
which have been linked to
autoimmunity in preclinical studies.
Or the decrease in animal protein
may downregulate IGF-1,
which is not just a cancer-
promoting growth hormone,
but may play a role in
autoimmune diseases as well.
Or it could be the good stuff in
plants that may protect cells,
like the polyphenol phytochemicals,
such as flavonoids found in plant foods.
Maybe it's the environmental toxins
that build up in the food chain.
For example, fish contaminated with
industrial pollutants, like PCBs,
are associated with increased
frequency of thyroid disorders.
Okay, what about the other autoimmune
thyroid disease, Hashimoto's thyroiditis,
which, assuming you're getting
enough iodine, is the primary cause
of hypothyroidism, an underactive
thyroid gland. Graves' disease
wasn't the only autoimmune disorder
that was rare or virtually unknown
among those living in rural sub-Saharan
Africa, eating near-vegan diets.
They also appeared to have less
Hashimoto's. There's evidence
that those with Hashimoto's have
compromised antioxidant status,
but we don't know if
it's cause or effect.
But if you look at the dietary factors
associated with blood levels
of autoimmune anti-thyroid antibodies,
animal fats seem to be associated
with higher levels,
whereas vegetables and other plant
foods are associated with lower levels.
So again, anti-inflammatory
diets may be useful.
No surprise, as Hashimoto's
is an inflammatory disease.
That's what thyroiditis means:
inflammation of the thyroid gland.
Another possibility is the reduction
in methionine intake, an amino acid
concentrated in animal protein, thought
to be one reason why the consumption
of whole plant foods is likely to have
a favorable influence on longevity,
through decreasing the risk of cancer,
heart disease, and diabetes.
And methionine restriction improves
thyroid function in mice,
but it has yet to be put to the test
for Hashimoto's in humans.
If you compare the poop of patients
with Hashimoto's to controls,
the condition appears to be
related to a clear reduction
in the concentration of Prevotella
species. Prevotella are good
fiber-eating bugs known to enhance
anti-inflammatory activities.
Decreased Prevotella levels
are also something you see in
other autoimmune conditions, such as
multiple sclerosis and type 1 diabetes.
How do you get more Prevotella?
Eat more plants.
But put a vegetarian on a diet
of meat, eggs, and dairy,
and within as few as four days
you can drive down levels.
So one would expect those eating plant-
based diets to have less Hashimoto's,
but in a previous video I expressed
concern about insufficient iodine intake,
which could also lead to hypothyroidism.
So, which is it?
Let's find out.
Vegan diets tended to be
associated with lower, not higher,
risk of hypothyroid disease.
Why the word "tended"?
Because the associated protection against
hypothyroidism incidence and prevalence
studies did not reach
statistical significance.
It wasn't just because they were slimmer.
The lower risk existed even after
controlling for body weight, so
they think maybe it's because
animal products may induce inflammation.
The question I have, though, is: if
someone who already has Hashimoto's,
I mean, what happens
if you change their diet?
That's exactly what I'll explore next.
Okay. So that was about preventing hypothyroidism
or hyperthyroidism, preventing Graves’ disease and
Hashimoto’s. But what about a dietary intervention
to treat Hashimoto’s, treat hypothyroidism? That’s
what we’ll close out with before I take questions:
a natural treatment for Hashimoto’s disease.
Autoimmune thyroiditis, also known as
Hashimoto's disease, is an organ-specific
autoimmune disorder where your body
attacks your own thyroid gland,
often leading to hypothyroidism
due to destruction and scarring
of the gland itself.
We know there's a genetic component,
since identical twins are more likely to
share the disease than fraternal twins.
However, even with identical twins,
the concordance rate was only about 50%,
meaning even if your identical twin,
with basically the exact same DNA as you,
has the disease, there's only like
a flip of a coin's chance you'll get it,
emphasizing that other important factors
other than your genes play a role
in the development of the disease.
Genes load the gun, but
environment may pull the trigger.
More than 90 chemicals have been
noted disrupting hormonal balance
or thyroid function; however, only
a few such pollutants show evidence
that they contribute to
autoimmune thyroid disease.
These include polyaromatic
hydrocarbons, which smokers
get a lot from their cigarettes,
but in nonsmokers, exposure
comes almost entirely from food.
Polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons are
primarily formed when muscle meats,
such as beef and pork, fish,
or chicken, are cooked
by high temperature methods
such as grilling.
PBBs are a type of flame-retardant
chemical no longer manufactured
in the U.S., but still found
in the aquatic food chain.
And PCBs are used in a number
of industrial processes and end up
in peoples' bodies largely through
the consumption of fish as well,
but also other meat and eggs.
So one might suspect those eating plant-
based diets would have lower rates
of hypothyroidism, and indeed,
despite their lower iodine intake,
vegan diets tended to be protective.
But they've never been put to
the test in an interventional trial.
A modification of the Paleolithic diet
has been tried in Hashimoto's patients,
but didn't appear to improve
thyroid function.
What did, though, was Nigella Sativa.
That name should sound familiar to anyone
who's read my latest book "How Not to Diet"
or watched my latest live presentation
"Evidence-Based Weight Loss."
Nigella Sativa is the sciency name
for black cumin, which is just
a simple spice, but it's also used
for a variety of medicinal purposes.
In this study, a randomized, double-blind
placebo-controlled trial of eight weeks
of a half teaspoon of powdered black
cumin a day in Hashimoto's patients.
Not only was there a significant
reduction in body weight,
which is why I profiled it in the book,
it also significantly reduced thyroid
stimulating hormone, a sign that
thyroid function was improving.
It even lowered the level of autoimmune
anti-thyroid antibodies, as well as
increasing blood levels of thyroid
hormone T3 in these Hashimoto's patients.
In addition, there was a significant
drop in Interleukin 23,
a proinflammatory cell signal thought to
help promote the autoimmune inflammation
of the thyroid, so further confirming
the anti-inflammatory nature of the plant.
And what were the side effects?
Well, a 17% drop in LDL bad cholesterol.
Given the fact that patients with
Hashimoto's may be at particularly
high risk of developing heart
disease, this is exactly
the kind of side effect we'd want.
Considering these health-promoting
effects of black cumin,
it can be considered as
a therapeutic approach
in the management of Hashimoto's-
related metabolic abnormalities.
A similar trial failed
to find a benefit though.
Same dose, same time frame, but no
significant changes in thyroid function.
In contrast with the last study, though,
they were not all Hashimoto's patients,
but rather hypothyroid for any reason,
and that may have diluted the results.
And it's possible that telling patients
to take the black cumin doses
with their thyroid hormone replacement
therapy may have interfered
with its absorption, similar
to other foods and drugs,
which is why patients are normally
told to take it on an empty stomach.
Since there are no downsides—
I mean, it's just a simple spice—
I figure, why not give it a try?
The worst that can happen
is you'll have tastier food.
So, a half teaspoon of powdered black cumin seeds
once a day on an empty stomach for Hashimoto
sufferers. For those of you watching who have this
disease, try it out. Let me know how it works.
Okay, it is time for me to take questions.
Let me just give NutritionFacts staff a few
minutes to compile them into a list for me. As
you can imagine, with thousands of attendees,
there are a gazillion questions, and lots
of them are duplicates. So you can try to
find out what the most common questions are
and put them all together into one question,
rather than just asking questions
that fewer people are interested in.
Okay. So if you have not already clicked
on the Q&A button to ask your questions,
now’s the time to do it. And I’ll
be back in five to go down the list.